<?xml version="1.0"?>

<config_bld>

<comment>
This is a configuration file for building CLM.  It is the file format
produced by the configure script to store a build configuration.  It
may also be read by the configure script (via setting the -defaults
option) to provide a default build configuration.

This file may be edited by hand to quickly customize a configuration.  If
hand editing is done it should be recognized that XML parser used to read
this file is not able to check the file for valid syntax.  Also, the
current parser places some restrictions on the normally valid XML syntax:
1. Attribute values must be enclosed in DOUBLE QUOTED STRINGS!!!
</comment>

<comment>
clm_bld    CLM build directory, contains .o and .mod files
clm_exedir Directory where CLM executable will be created
clm_root   Root directory of CLM distribution
usr_src    User source directories to prepend to the filepath.  Multiple directories
           are specified as a comma separated list with no embedded white space.
</comment>

<directories
clm_bld="."
clm_exedir="."
clm_root=""
usr_src=""
/>

<comment>
cpl     Is flux coupler used?  [ on | off ]
bgc     BGC mode:  [ none | cn | casa | dgvm ]
supln   Turn on CN supplemental nitrogen: [ on | off ]
rtm     Turn on RTM : [on | off ]
voc     Turn on VOC : [on | off ]
dust    Turn on DUST: [on | off ]
</comment>

<cppvars
cpl="off"
bgc="none"
supln="off"
voc="off"
dust="off"
rtm="off"
maxpft="4"
/>

<comment>
clm_exe    Name of CLM executable
cppdefs    User specified CPP defines to append to Makefile defaults.
cc         User specified C compiler overrides Makefile default (linux only).
cflags     User specified C compiler options to append to Makefile defaults.
fc         User specified Fortran compiler overrides Makefile default.
debug      Switch to enable debugging options for Fortran compiler.
fflags     User specified Fortran compiler flags to append to Makefile defaults.
fopt       User specified Fortran optimization flags to override Makefile defaults.
ldflags    User specified load options to append to Makefile defaults.
spmd       Switch to enable or disable building SPMD version of CLM.
smp        Switch to enable or disable building SMP version of CLM.
nc_inc     Directory containing NetCDF include files.
nc_lib     Directory containing NetCDF library.
nc_mod     Directory containing NetCDF module files.
esmf_mod   Directory containing ESMF module files (if linking to external ESMF)
esmf_lib   Directory containing ESMF library      (if linking to external ESMF)
mpi_inc    Directory containing MPI include files.
mpi_lib    Directory containing MPI library.
mpi_lib_name Name of MPI library.
target_os  OS for which CLM is being built.
</comment>

<makefile
clm_exe="clm"
cppdefs=""
cc=""
fc=""
debug="0"
cflags=""
fflags=""
fopt=""
ldflags=""
spmd=""
smp=""
nc_inc=""
nc_lib=""
nc_mod=""
mpi_inc=""
mpi_lib=""
mpi_lib_name=""
target_os=""
esmf_mod=""
esmf_lib=""
/>

</config_bld>






