<appendix id="editing_templates">
<title>Editing Template Files Before Configure</title>
<para>
The last kind of customization that you can do for a case, before configure is run 
is to edit the templates. The clm template is in
<filename>models/lnd/clm/bld/clm.cpl7.template</filename>, the datm template is
in <filename>models/atm/datm/bld/datm.cpl7.template</filename>, and the driver templates
are in the <filename>models/drv/bld</filename> directory and are named:
<filename>ccsm.template</filename> and <filename>cpl.template</filename>. When a case is
created they are also copied to the <filename>Tools/Templates</filename> directory 
underneath your case. If you want to make changes that will impact all your cases, you
should edit the template files under the <filename>models</filename> directory, but
if you want to make a change ONLY for a particular case you should edit the template
under that specific case.
</para>
<note>
<para>
Editing the template files is NOT for the faint of heart! We recommend this ONLY for
experts! It's difficult to do because the template is a script that actually creates 
another script. So part of the script is echoing the script to be created and part of
it is a script that is run when "configure -case" is run. As a result any variables 
in the part of the script that is being echoed have to be escaped like this:
<screen width="99">
\$VARIABLE
</screen>
But, in other parts of the script that is run, you can NOT escape variables. So you 
need to understand if you are in a part of the script that is echoing the script to
be created, or in the part of the script that is actually run.
</para>
</note>
<para>
If you can customize your case using: compsets, <filename>env_*.xml</filename> variables,
or a user namelist, as outlined in <xref linkend="customize"></xref> you should do so.
The main reason to actually edit the template files, is if you are in a situation where
the template aborts when you try it run it when "configure -case" is run. The other
reason to edit the template is if you are CLM developer and need to make adjustments
to the template because of code or script updates.
</para>
<para>
The outline of the clm template is as follows:
<screen width="99">
# set up options for clm configure and then run clm configure
$CODEROOT/lnd/clm*/bld/configure &lt;options&gt;
# set up options for clm build-namelist and then run clm build-namelist
$CODEROOT/lnd/clm*/bld/build-namelist &lt;options&gt;
# echo the $CASEBUILD/clm.buildnml.csh script out
cat &gt;! $CASEBUILD/clm.buildnml.csh &lt;&lt; EOF1
# NOTE: variables in this section must be escaped
EOF1
# Remove temporary namelist files

# echo the $CASEBUILD/clm.buildexe.csh script out
cat &gt; $CASEBUILD/clm.buildexe.csh &lt;&lt;EOF2
# NOTE: variables in this section must be escaped
EOF2
# Remove temporary configure files
</screen>
</para>
</appendix>

<appendix id="runinit_ibm.csh">
<title>Using the Script <filename>runinit_ibm.csh</filename> to both Run &clm; and
Interpolate Datasets</title>
<para>
The script <filename>runinit_ibm.csh</filename> can be used on the
<acronym>NCAR</acronym> bluefire machine to run &clm; to create a template file and
then run <command>interpinic</command> and do this over a variety of standard
resolutions. By default it is setup to loop over the following resolutions:
<screen width="99">
foreach res ( "1.9x2.5" "10x15" "4x5" "0.9x1.25" "2.5x3.33" "0.47x0.63" "48x96" )
</screen>
It is also only setup to run &clmcn; and only particular masks for each resolution.
But, the script can be modified by the user to run over whatever list you would like it
to. It is also hooked up to the &buildnml; XML database, so will only use the
datasets that are part of the database, see <xref linkend="adding_files"></xref>
to see how to add files to the database. The script runs &clm; only using OpenMP
threading and as such can be run interactively, but it can also be submitted to the
batch que.
</para>
<warning>
<para>
There is a known problem running <filename>runinit_ibm.csh</filename>. You will
need to fix this before using it. See the <filename>KnownBugs</filename> file
for bug # 1258. It gives changes that you need to make to get it to work.
</para>
</warning>
</appendix>

<appendix id="testing">
<title>Scripts for testing &clm;</title>

<para>
Technically, you could use the customization we gave in <xref linkend="customize"></xref>
to test various configuration and namelist options for &clm;. Sometimes, it's also
useful to have automated tests though to test that restarts give exactly the same 
results as without a restart. It's also useful to have automated tests to run over a
wide variety of configurations, resolutions, and namelist options. To do that we have
several different types of scripts set up to make running comprehensive testing of
&clm; easy. There are two types of testing scripts for &clm;. The first are the &cesm;
test scripts, which utilize the <command>create_newcase</command> scripts that we
shown how to use in this User's Guide. The second are a set of stand-alone scripts that
use the &clm; &configure; and &buildnml; scripts to build and test the model as well as
testing the &clm; tools as well. Below we will go into further details of how to use
both methods.
</para>

<sect1 id="cesm_testing">
<title>Testing &clm; Using the &cesm; Test Scripts</title>

<para>
We first introduce the test scripts that work for all CESM components. We will
use the <command>create_test</command> and then the <command>create_test_suite</command>
scripts. The <command>create_test</command> runs a specific type of test, at a given
resolution, for a given compset using a given machine. There is a list of different
tests, but the "ERI" tests do several things at once, running from startup, as well
as doing exact branch and restart tests. So to run "ERI" testing at 2-degree with
the I1850CN compset on bluefire you do the following.
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_test -testname ERI.f19_g16.I1850CN.bluefire
> cd ERI.f19_g16.I1850CN.bluefire.$id
> ./ERI.f19_g16.I1850CN.bluefire.$id.build
> ERI.f19_g16.I1850CN.bluefire.$id.submit
</screen>
When the test is done it will update the file <filename>TestStatus</filename> with
either a PASS or FAIL message.
</para>
<para>
To run a suite of tests from a list of tests with syntax similar to above you use
<command>create_test_suite</command> as follows passing it a ASCII list of tests.
There are already some test lists in the
<filename>scripts/ccsm_utils/Testlists</filename> directory a few of which are specific
to &clm;. To run for the &clm; bluefire test list, on bluefire, you would do the
following:
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_test_suite -input_list ccsm_utils/Testlists/bluefire.clm.auxtest
# Submit the suite of tests (note $id refers to the integer job number for this job)
> ./cs.submit.$id.bluefire
# Later check the tests with...
> ./cs.status.$id
# The above will give a PASS or FAIL message for each test.
</screen>
For more information on doing testing with the &cesm; scripts see the
<ulink url="&cesmwebmodelrel;cesm">&cesm1;
User's Guide</ulink> on testing.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="clm_standalone_testing">
<title>Testing &clm; Using the &clm; Stand-Alone Testing Scripts</title>

<para>
In the <filename>models/lnd/clm/test/system</filename> directory there is
a set of test scripts that is specific to stand-alone &clm;. It does testing
on configurations harder to test for in the &cesm; test scripts, and also allows
you to test the &clm; tools such as <command>mkgriddata</command> and 
<command>mksurfdata</command>. The main driver script is called
<filename>test_driver.sh</filename> and it can run both interactively as well as being
submitted to the batch queue. Like other scripts you can get help on it by running the 
"-help" option as: <command>test_driver.sh -help</command>. 
There is also a <filename>README</filename>
file that gives details about environment variables that can be given to
<command>test_driver.sh</command> to change it's operation.
</para>
<para>
To submit a suite of stand-alone tests to the batch que:
<screen width="99">
> cd models/lnd/clm/test/system
> ./test_driver.sh
</screen>
You can also run tests interactively:
<screen width="99">
> cd models/lnd/clm/test/system
> ./test_driver.sh -i
</screen>
The output of the help option is as follows:
<screen width="99">
&clmtestdriver;
</screen>
A table of the list of tests and the machines they are run on is available from:
<ulink url="../../test/system/test_table.html">test_table.html</ulink>
</para>
</sect1>

</appendix>
<appendix id="doc_build">
<title>Building the Users-Guide Documentation for &clm;</title>
<para>
All of the documentation for &clm; can be built using GNU Makefiles that are
available in the appropriate directories. The Makefiles require the following 
utilities: <command>docbook2html</command>, <command>docbook2pdf</command>, 
<command>protex</command>, and <command>latex2html</command>.
</para>
<para>
To build the Users Guide for &clm; (requires docbook).
<screen width="99">
> cd models/lnd/clm/doc/UsersGuide
> gmake
</screen>
Note, that when the Users-Guide is built it will get output from other &clm;
utilities that by nature abort, and hence stop the make from continuing. However,
this is expected so you should simply run <command>gmake</command> again until
it either completes or comes upon a legitimate issue. Here is what a sample
warning looks like when <command>gmake</command> is run.
<screen width="99">
The following line will fail in the make as it calls die -- but that is expected
Check that the output config_help.tlog is good and redo your make
../../bld/configure -help >& config_help.tlog
make: *** [config_help.tlog] Error 255
</screen>
To build the Code Reference Guide for &clm; (requires <command>protex</command> and
<command>latex2html</command>). The make here uses a <filename>Filepath</filename>
file that points to the list of directories that you want <command>protex</command>
to run over. You should examine this file and make sure it is appropriate for what
you need to do, before running the make.
<screen width="99">
> cd models/lnd/clm/doc/CodeReference
> gmake
</screen>
To build the table of tests for the &clm; test suite. The make here runs a UNIX
shell script to create a html table of the list of tests run on the different machines
from the &clm; test suite.
<screen width="99">
> cd models/lnd/clm/test/system
> gmake
</screen>

</para>

</appendix>
